On April 12th, 2025, a Dutch politician
said something strange.  For it
cannot be the case that people in the city have to
outbid each other by hundreds of thousands, while
the meadows lie fallow just outside that city
.  And that is why I say the
most important breakthrough for now is to do whatever it takes
to build 10 new cities in the coming years
with green
neighborhoods where children can
play safely with amenities nearby and
where everyone can find a nice home again
.
In a country where being normal is air
this was weird.  Building 10 new cities
tove a housing crisis seems more like a
policy by child
was alone.  We are closing Tatasel and rebuilding it
into Tatastad.
Residential areas, not airports—that is what
we stand for.  In an election where housing
is the biggest issue of all.  Multiple
parties have gone so far to push for
entirely new cities to tackle the
problem of two few homes.
The plan for 10 cities is now the
biggest of them all.  So we asked the
leader of the party to speak with us
about what could be one of the biggest
mega projects in Dutch history.
This is a video on how to bring down the
cost in time of building in one of the
inflexible housing marets on the planet.
How to create places people actually
live in how to solve the Dutch housing
crisis.   "
We don't know" comes across as
very negative, and for me,
I think the most important explanation
for this is that we have made it so complicated
to build at all.
Just after the Second World War, the
Netherlands was traumatized.
The hunger winter killed thousands of
people food security national security.
The Dutch Minister of Agriculture and
Future European Commissioner for
Agriculture believed small traditional
farms were inefficient.  He designed the
EU's common agricultural policy
guaranteeing farmers subsidies in order
to prevent the risks of fame.
Meanwhile, only 28% of Dutch households
own their home.  Renting was the norm,
but then things started to change.  The
mortgage interest rate deduction
stimulated people to acquire even
largeres and owning homes.  Renters
spurred into becoming owners.  The number
of houses grew, but it wasn't enough.
The quality of existing homes was poor.
The pipe in Amsterdam was a working
class neighborhood.  People were stuck in
cramped low quality apartments.  In order
to address postw reconstruction, the
Dutch government passed the law
introducing a new system for how the
scar land in the country should be used.
The Ministry of Public Housing and
spatial planning was established while
the countries set up a decentralized
system for urban planning.  Farmers
dealing with scarce land began to
intensify their farms.  Cheap imported
feed crew tons of livestock.  Artificial
fertilizers push crop yields further.
In c municipal governments created new
zoning plans.
Yakama was a modernist who believed in
tall buildings providing public space from
shared infrastructure and large
apartments without sacrificing green
space.  His plan for Amsterdam was to
build an elongated series of islands
reclimate from the connection to the city
with a 14 lane highway and monorail
pampus residential towers up to 40
floors t00
people completely unheard of at the time
but a drastic solution to two few and
two poor quality homes
increased the housing supply by building
an entirely new city not too close and
not too
eno
an is better to build on land instead
the city approved a new modern
neighborhood filled with highrised
towers on the periphery of  the city the
belm
the municipality strictly defined how
land could be used in each are green
only residential large tower block the
planners reacted to overcreded homes and
factories built next to schools
develers
arch
of housing stock was built between 195
and 1975
social housing was backed by generous
national funding the share of rental
stock provided by housing associations
reached 80% in the city there were no
income limit doctors and nurses lived in
the same mixed neighborhoods
but the new housed
form
increasedly housing people althice
vacancies  and crime increased the top
planning was criticized across the
Netherlands old neighborhoods demolished;
unpopular planning
in the old heart of Utrecht; much
will still have to disappear.
protest against the planned demolition
of still usable homes and against
further degradation of the environment
of the old city center.  Among other things
due to the projected access roads.
Municipalities formalized a process
giving residency.
They established an objection system
that applied to all government decisions
including building permits and zoning
plans.
By the 90s owner occupied housing
increased to more than 40% of the
housing stock.
Instead of the modernist towers, people
moved to new garden cities like Almerea
and Lady Stad.  Then the municipalities
expanded outwards with lower density
housing.  Venexwijken one of the largest
increases to Dutch housing stock over a
single period.  It provided for families
a suburban lifestyle but not for
everyone.  When CI became more valuable
they didn't do enough to allow the
demand in the new valuable urban areas.
They were criticized for becoming sleep
cities places where you sleep but have
to leave to do everything else instead
in Ceno
in planning became some valuable landus
became a VX by 2008 the Netherlands had
one of the highest private debt to GDP
ratios in the world built on cheap tax
subsided deb
more than half the Dutch housing stock
became owner occupied
CR
this to crunchly of hes decline in
financing construction
in orderover state debs instead of
decreasing the tax rebates to home
owners the government criticized austerity
policies and taxed housing  associations.
Social housing was restricted to only
the lowest income groups and the
government encouraged them to sell their
properties off to private investors.  At
the same time more young people started
living alone further raising demand for
space older people live longer too.  The
intensive agriculture and farming
subsidies of the last century were also
starting to have visible effects.  Run
from nitrogen fertilizers both in maner
and artificial cause damage.
could increase nitrogen around protected
natural areas frozen.  Thousands of
construction projects were put on hold.
It all to a wicked problem.  The
Netherlands has one of the worst housing
crises in Europe.  Even Ireland and
Canada are now competing more houses per
capita.
Speaking of a terrible combination of
market forces and state provided goods,
in order to produce this video fast, we
wanted to use BUE of Dutch cities.  So
after spending 15 minutes filling out a
form from a public media repository that
we thought made it a public good, we
asked to use one minute of footage.
After only waiting two whole days for a
response, they asked us to pay 1000 for
only aye license, a handling fee of 0,
and a download fee of 1620.
Clearly, traditional media licensing is
a bit outdated.  Luckily we have Story
Blocks, the sponsor of this video.
Instead of communicating with dinosaurs,
story blocks puts everything into one
place for one predictable cost.  They have
unlimited downloads with no hidden fees.
Everything is 100% royalty free with the
highest legal protection in the
industry.  The quality is great.  They
have real footage from artists and
filmmakers worldwide, not generic
corporate stock.
Also, if you're a premier user, they
have a plugin that lets you drag clips
straight into your timeline without
leaving the software.  Check it out now
at hook.best/storyblocks
and for a limited time, you can get two
extra months free with annual plans.
But why are some places still so much
better at responding to increases in
demand compared with the Netherlands?
Tokyo has avoided a housing crisis
despite an increasing population.  In
Europe, Vienna has also avoided a
housing crisis despite an increasing
population.  These two cities are really
different.  Vienna has a history of
funding state supported housing to keep
row.  They kept it available for a wide
range of income groups.  The apartments
are high quality.  Almost half of Vienna
is social housing and private rent is
also kept low.  Tokyo on the other hand
has very little public housing.  Instead,
it has some of the lowest barriers for
construction.  In the world, houses
decide quickly and the zoning code is
standardized and simple are very few
rules on the types of buildings
new buildings do approval processed
cansue building permits.
What exactly is the vision of
Dutch politics and Dutch
society on how we are
going to build a million new homes in the coming years?  Because
suppose you were to put those million houses
only in the existing city, then yes,
you also have to ask yourself the question: what
kind of neighborhoods and districts do
we want?  Are we really going to
build on open space everywhere, so that you
can stay neatly within the city limits and
say: "I only did infill development
."  But what did you give up, then?
How many playgrounds, green areas, and
other spatial spaces have been
lost that we actually
consider very important as well?  The reason the
Netherlands has a special problem.  is
because it has liberalized and
subsidized its demand side by actively
spurring housing ownership and at the
same time it has a highly regulated
supply side that makes it more difficult
and costly to build with generous
opportunities for public objection and
excessive building codes.   The
Netherlands really stands out in a very negative way,
and for me, I think the most
important explanation for this is that we
have made it so complicated to
build at all.  Um, as
Minister for Climate and Energy, I
experienced that as well with the energy transition.  Then
you have a plan together.  You actually know
exactly what you want to build
and deliver.  And the building itself
might take a year or a year and a half.  Um,
but the whole run-up to it, uh, many, many
years.
Speak with enough Dutch people above the
age of 50 who also travel to Belgium and
they laugh at how disorganized the
buildings and cities are.  This makes the
loose ownership of Tokyo impossible.  In the
case that you need homes quickly and the
market, then you would at least expect
to rely on a state that can produce
imperfect but big housing projects and
fast track new construction.  That will
at least curren seeking and unnecessary
speculation.
But the capacity to build social housing
in the Netherlands has been labomized.
Housing corporations have been defunded
and social housing has not been able to
compete on construction prices private
developers
country ne barriers development to the
state capacity to build social housing
like in Vienna.  Over
the past 20 years, the government has naturally increasingly
withdrawn from the theme of
public housing or the housing market, or whatever
you want to call it.  Um, and
at the same time, uh, a housing cooperative is
given less financial clout, uh, and private parties
find the Dutch government
unpredictable and don't really know
where to invest.  Out on the
policies that subsidize the buying of homes
the result is a housing price grossly
artificially inflated.  Look, much
more supply will hopefully, at
some point, help to
cool down that housing market a bit.  But
we also just have to honestly acknowledge
that, um, in the Netherlands we
have tax rules that simply don't work, eh,
if you want to curb house prices.
And even if you tackle these problems,
there's still a lasting concern about
whether the new places you build will
actually be desirable.
Unfortunate a lot of what was charming
about the old CI has been limited.
When my dad was a student studied from
low ceiling beams in Amsterdam that kind
of unit hard to build because of ceiling
and door mandates.  That is also reduce
number of units that can be placed in a
building.  We have a reflex to regulate,
whereby we essentially
want to shut down everything that has ever gone wrong with
new rules.  And that is all well-
intentioned, because at some point someone
got sick or perhaps died, or
somewhere a piece of a, uh, beautiful, uh
ecosystem was, uh, destroyed because we were, uh,
too clumsy with it.  And yet,
the reflex is always to add even more new
rules.  Uh, which sometimes
makes things more complicated, more complex, and
also makes money off of all sorts of parties,
uh, because they can just about see the forest for the trees
and, uh, then start selling you all sorts of
reports, uh, just so you can uh, hand in
your checklist to the government again
.  Um, and sometimes,
uh, I think it's also good to
go all the way back to the source for a moment, uh,
and also ask yourself: is this
really necessary?  Steep staircases have
also been restricted in new buildings.
They have to have a specific depth to
height ratio and in some cases a second
staircase for emergencies.
Today, at least 55% of new dwellings
usable floor area must comply with
standards for daylight.  This makes
traditional architecture hard to build.
It makes it more expensive and it makes
it take longer.  Buildings built near
railines have to be sound professional against
the theoretical 65 debs because that's
what the railway is permitted for.  If
they don't, they're not legal.  All the
while this is Japan.
Besides the fact that young people can
choose whether they want to live next to
a railway or not, modern trains
practically never exceed 53 debs.  Only
about one of the volume of the buildings
have to be soundprof.  In the
Netherlands, there were plans to build
student housing for 5000 students.  It
was stopped because of noise concerns
from being too close to Schipol airport.
Meanwhile, there was a 197.
Yeah, all those well-intentioned rules
mainly protect all the people who are
well-off, who already have a nice house
, who thanks to those rules
can always keep their view or
hold up a housing project for years, while those outsiders
just can't get in.
paringots renters buyers need munpalit
mandate parking spaces for an entirely
new housing project in was stopped
because parking requirements stipulated
16 spaces when they were supposed to
round up to7 the liberal party has
decided to do the incred
1.7
Mpality pushes for new apartments to
have garages on the ground floor for
bicycles that no one asked for.  It also
means ground space that can be taken up
by a nice small cafe or small sh is
occupied by underused bike parking
garage.  Elderly people with more room
than they need can see their state
pension payments cut if they decide to
anotherion.
If they do have a spare room theyd like
to rent out, the paperwork have to go
through to do that with peace of mind is
intense.  Amsterdam pass legislation
restricting the amount of people that
can be put in a single house because of
course that's an incredibly rational
policy when dealing with scarcity and
students intents.  If there's a homeless
person outside sleeping on a bench, why
not just get rid of the bench?  That is
quite a bill, so to speak; if you are
indeed on a certain form of
social security, but you have
people moving in with you, then
we are going to cut your benefits.  Yes, none of that is
conducive.  Um, and it was also once well-
intentioned to prevent people from
making unnecessarily large claims on, uh,
collective provisions and on our
tax money.  But the societal
damage caused by those housemates is
by now much greater.  So how can you do
that again, how can you reach a
new balance there?   to
all these rules are stocked on top of
each other understandable
goes up private and social housing so
it's not particularly surprising that
parties are now considering radical
supply side solution
the country needs over 900,000 new homes
by 2030 with a current shortfall of over
400,000
the left liberal progressive party vault
proposed to close the tata steel factory
andlace it with city the green Social
democratic party to shut down airports
and build new cities on them.  The right
populist party proposed demolishing the
Hilvers media park and building a new
neighborhood on it.  The Christian
Democrats presented a plan for few additional
villages.
But the most ambitious proposal was by
day 66 for 10 entirely new cities.
And why 10?  Why not 11, 12, 9?  Yes.
Well, that is also a bit, um, yeah,
just a nice number, I have to say.
Um, because I, uh, I got
provinces on the line pretty quickly saying: "Yes,
but are we included in those 10? Because
every province wants a new city."  So
okay, 12 is allowed too.  Um, but it was also
a bit simplistic thinking, based on the idea that you have
a housing shortage that you
can partially solve with more shared housing, uh,
converting vacant buildings, uh, building
in the existing city, and whatever you are left with in terms
of the housing construction challenge, well,
then you have 10 uh, average cities in terms of size.
The first city they published
plans for was IT a city between Alma and
Amsterdam
a city built on water on an entirely new
polder to solve the largest housing
crisis in the country
very similar to plan pampus like Bama
there still an open question about
whether building a polder is remotely
affordable especially compared with
building on land next to the city
itself.  Yes, there are a few very nice
uh options.  Um look, I think
Havenstad in Amsterdam is a uh
very suitable location anyway.  There are already
very concrete plans, but the
central government also needs to help a bit
to realize the right facilities
.  Uh, recently a number of
architects made an inventory
of how you can add 100,000 homes in Rotterdam
.  And they also said
to me then: "That is also, uh, the new
Rotterdam as an extra city."
Um, but besides the IJstad, a beautiful island
between Amsterdam and Almere, I am thinking
of the clog near Veenendaal, among others
.  Um, that is also a region
where, uh, accessibility is very good
.  You have public transport there, you know, with fast
train connections to the whole country,
good highways, but also a whole lot of
employment opportunities nearby.  Um, and
that is really a nice location to, uh,
realize a lot of housing development as well.  Uh, I
am a big supporter of a
new high-speed rail line from Amsterdam
via Verleverland to Friesland and
Groningen.  preferably then on to
Germany and Denmark, of course.  But that
would create a lot of opportunities at Heerenveen and Groningen
to
really realize large-scale new
housing development there.  Um, and yes, I might as
well mention that one—I would
n't have thought of it myself—but in Zeeland you have a
very nice, creative idea for the city
on the Sloe as well.  Um, that is a bit less
large-scale than I have ice cream in mind
.  Um, but there you could also
show in a new way how the
Netherlands can live and work with the
water, right, with the city built partly in the
water, with water homes,
floating homes.  Well, there are
all kinds of really cool ideas from
architects there.  But that is
actually how you should look at every region:
how can you really add quality here as well?
So, uh, a number of the
examples.
In order to bring down costs, they wanna
rely on modular construction.  This
building offsite with prefabricated
modules that will definitely make things
cheaper but there are trade ofs.  I
always get the creeps from neighborhoods
or streets where every house
looks exactly the same and you think:
"Yeah, if this were a completely different
postcode, it would have
looked exactly the same, right?" That is that copying of the
same streets throughout the country
. Um, I also have friends living in a
new-build neighborhood. There, you could also
get an interior design package from the
contractor. And then it turned out that five neighbors in
a row
had all chosen that same interior design package. So
those houses weren't just the same on the
outside, but on the
inside too. Well, I don't think that's
something you can successfully sustain for very long
. So, with those
new cities, you just want to agree to challenge
architects to come up with very
different concepts. That
all facades have something playful and something
different about them. That is why the old
inner cities of the Netherlands are so incredibly
attractive. Because it
creates such an incredibly diverse streetscape where there is
always something different to see and
discover. And the beauty of it now,
I think, with the emerging modular building, is that
you  Yeah, maybe in 20 or 30 years you'll
find a really ugly facade anyway, and then you
can screw a new facade back on,
without having to destroy all those materials
because we can reuse them smartly
. In the 60s, a man named
Nicholas Habraken quickly saw the
problems with mass monotonous housing
that happened during the post-war
reconstruction.
At the same time, he also saw the
benefits of lower construction costs.
If the industrialization of housing could
bring down costs, it could also mean
there were more options for
flexibility in new building types. He
believed houses could be specifically
tailored to the buyer. Like a car
dealership, a couple would look at different
types of homes and different types of
features, and they would be prefabricated and
then constructed on top of a uniform
structure. The inside of the building
could also be quickly changed to
the homeowner's updating preferences.
For the time, this was a quite wild
suggestion.
Look, for a long time, when it came to modular
building, I thought of the shipping containers in
Amsterdam-Noord. And that's because when
I was studying, two friends of mine had
their student rooms in those shipping containers,
and they were... that was  also
literally just stacked shipping containers into which
a shower and a kitchenette had been
installed. And as students, they were
super happy with it. But I think that for a
very long time, people thought: "Yes, yes, yes,
I want, I want more than that."  I want something
that has a lot more look, that
has high-quality materials, eh."
Well, fortunately there are now a
number of Dutch companies that are
doing a really fantastic job with all kinds of
different variants of
facade cladding.
I feel like this kind of way of building
is very different from how people around
me typically interact with buying homes.
On the one hand, if I speak with a
friend who works at a consultancy,
they'll try and tell me, Elmer, it's a
good investment and it would be dumb not
to and it's only going to get  harder.
On the other hand, if I speak with my
champ social democrats, hold spe about
why a house is not an investment. And did you know
People with a new job can get access to
a second one without breaking the bank
I need to. The cost of producing
them has also steadily declined  for
years.  Of course, it raises occasionally
with inflation, but I can get a
relatively cheap car in the United
States and Europe provided by mainly
private companies.  I can get one from
China where they generously state
backed.  But with all that said, if I
told my parents and my friends I bought
a car as a long-term investment, they
would look at me like I'm a [ __ ].  And
that's because the moment I drive a car,
it depreciates, it loses quality and
declines in value.  A car is investment
in the sense can go places that other
would.  I can eat food in a parking spot
when I can't find a table.
But for most people, a car is not a good
investment in the sense that you would
put large parts of your income on it
in the hope that you can sell it at a
higher price in the future.  So why is a
house so different?
also falling apart
strang
why does it work like that in the Netherlands?  Why
is that what we put all our
effort into?
Yes, that is a very good question, because a
lot of people also think: "Yes, I
must have that house, because  "That's just
a little something for a rainy day
later."
Yes. Uh, whereas in other countries you look for that much
more in other forms of
investment, stocks, bonds,
saving more for your pension, you name it
. But because of the
system we have in the Netherlands,
because of the housing market we have, and
those rising house prices throughout the year
, it has also become a self-filling prophecy
, that owning a house is your way of
eventually making much more money
. For almost the past 10 years, it
was impossible to fight against that. Almost.
In 1858, a man was walking around California.
He saw rapid progress; the
transcontinental railroad was
constructed, supposed to be in a rapid era
of innovations and human improvement, but
next to that rapid progress, he saw
poverty. People squeezed for rent, trying
to get access to the valuable
opportunities in the city.
He was overlooking San Francisco Bay and
asked a man passing by how much the land
was worth. The man said that lander over
yonder
howled it for 000.
All the man on the horde was a greenfield
with some cows. Families  that live in
Amsterdam were fortunate enough to buy
homes in the city for much lower value
than they currently are.  Over years of
them living there, young people,
entrepreneurs and families have come in
and made the city a much more pleasant
place to live in.  The government built
metros, schools, and parks.  Meanwhile,
their property degraded with water
damage and broken bricks.  But they grew
more wealthy.
And that's because people can build
railroads, construct factories, provide
services, create productive agricultural
fields, and take financial risk.  But all
of it will increase the value of one
thing above all else land.
Unlike other factors of production, land
is special.  It is the most ignored but
it must come before anything occurs.
Fossil fuels are responsible for
overconfident Norwegians.  The silicon in
the GPU is used to power by render farm
super luminal.  Check it out.  Discount in
the description, no shame.  And the country
that cities grow on top of and people
compete to take part in.  But you can't
produce more land like you can produce
more goods, services, labor or capital.
People housing value does not rise
because the building appreciates.  They
rise because  The value of the land on
appreciates faster than the actual house
can desire. As a society grows more
productive, other people want to join
in. A hairdresser who contributes labor
is rewarded with a wage. If she saves
some of that wage and takes a risk to
invest it in starting a new company,
she becomes a capitalist. But the
landowner the hairdresser is rewarded
simply for holding the title to the
peace of earth and for making all other people
around her more valuable.
As a result of generous procedures, a
third of the new build homes in the
Netherlands face objections from locals
trying to object
. It is also important. Being able to object
is also important, because
mistakes are simply made in
decision-making sometimes. But let's
flatten that into doing it right the first time.
And if you suffer damage, also a
decent compensation for
any damage. But in a
way that we can also help the outsiders again
by drawing up housing construction lots
.
Even Mona Keizer, the current minister
of housing and special planning, blocked
housing in her own backyard.  Despite
being a front runner for the farmers
party, she blocked an apartment complex
for old people with dementia, arguing it
potentially release too much nitrogen.
When the supply of new places is kept
artificially low, even those who are
better at constructing more units for
lower costs.
Developers honor to build.
Mean the random fraternity dude in can
house will be fine.
The man Henry George went on to publish
a book called progress and poverty.  In
he argued that the fairest tax was a tax
on the unknown value of land.
Today economists from across the
political spectrum resoundingly agree
that the land value tax is one of the
largest and fairest taxes of all.  Even
if they debate the exact revenue can
generate or how easy it is to
administer.  When Gorbov was transforming
the Soviet Union into a market-based
economy, seeing a unique opportunity for
fresh start, economist through the west
argued that he should avoid their own
country historical mistakes.  Their key
advice to encourage him to build
economic system that is fundamentally on
a land value tax.
Instead, the Dutch government pushed the
opposite.  They gave out housing
subsidies and actively encouraged people
to take on as much debt as  possible,
allowing them to bid for higher and
higher inflated land values. This
country has one of the most
distortionary tax systems in Europe, and
it has actively reduced property taxes
that, all beat imperfectly, could still
capture some of the unarned value of
land. Even Texas, of all places, has a
higher effect of property tax than we
do. Maybe we should also give them
a bit of, well, a little push in
the right direction somewhere. Moving away from
putting money into houses, for example
through a higher home ownership
tax or,
you know, a land tax, for
instance. Is that something you are
also looking into, or what is your stance on that
? Look, in
recent years, various
independent people have
conducted evaluations of what constitutes
effective tax measures in the Netherlands, both
in collecting and refunding
tax money. And that
turned out to be quite a critical report, and that is putting it
mildly. So you could
really radically simplify the Dutch tax system,
so that you
are circulating much more money.
And it also prevents a
whole lot of people from
getting into trouble precisely because regulations aren't good.
are exploited that the government
has not handled that well.
If you save money in the Netherlands
instead of investing that into something
new, the most obvious tax advantage
thing to do is put it into a house.
We have much too high taxes on
work. Um, which is also just not
good for the money you have left at the end
of the month. But it is also not
good for the increase in
labor productivity or
enticing people to work more hours.
In very many cases,
people think, "Well, I would like to go from three to four
days," or from 3 to 4.5. But it
yields me little net benefit. I would be
crazy to do that. It is simply
not good for the economy and our
collective prosperity. You see that we
tax far too little, specifically on
pollution. CO2 emissions, the pollution
of water, the destruction of our
nature. That is almost always, yes, more or
less free or at a much too low
price. And what we also tax too little
are assets. And whether those assets
are in real estate or in enormous
fortunes.  on bank accounts,
stocks, et cetera. Um, that
wealth inequality is only getting
bigger. Um, and the tax benefits
are there for the homeowner, but not
for the people in the rental property.
So, left with a country whose primary
wealth is holding land. Not wealthy
because of hard working or skilled
labor, risk or innovation, but because
of the artificially inflated value of
land. That's not progressive or
conservative, left or right, big
business or small. It's just cringe. 10
new cities is a good idea. Purely if it can
attack inflated land values. Whether it
takes extreme market dynamism in housing,
it doesn't matter. If anything, the plan
doesn't go far enough.
One of the biggest issues with new
developments is that it takes time to
develop. New areas can be empty and unused. I
was in Brandenvoort near Helmond myself just two weeks ago
. That is really
a beautiful district, which is
relatively far from the city center,
with very beautiful residential architecture
that looks a bit like the 1930s
or the canal belts of  the cities in
the Randstad. Um, they really
thought very carefully about the schools, the
sports facilities, a community
center, and a library there. All of
that is there.
Yes. But everyone who lives there
complains that they miss the little café or a
nice restaurant. Or, so
those people also say, yes, if they were to
start over, we wouldn't just want two supermarkets and the library in the
center of this new district,
but specifically
a small square with nice hospitality venues
. So there... But that does require a
government that thinks about it itself,
because that project developer
naturally thinks primarily in the first instance about
how I can build houses as quickly as possible
and make money from them, and hospitality.
Yes, if there aren't enough people living there yet,
I won't be able to rent out those square meters
. So I might as well
put an apartment in there too. Um, uh, so
thinking very carefully about how you, from day
one, also simply add the coziness and the
amenities.
Although most of Amsterdam was zoned for mixed
use, when comparing the Pipe with
Iybergh today, you'll notice the  clear
difference in what people are allowed to
build.  The main goal of zoning was to
prevent existential risk.  It should
prevent bad air quality near children
which country is already not doing well
enough t steel or in Amsterdam north.
Zoning is not supposed to make it
difficult to start a restaurant next to
housing because god forbid a person
above the age of 65s it's a bit too
loud.  It's never gna happen but just
imagine we had zoning in cascading
categories.  Imagine if the liberal
parties in this country actually acted
like liberals and had no parking
minimums at all.  Why do people without
cars have to pay for those with them?
It's important for people to be able to
complain and protest against massive
developments very person who has
affable housing underented.
The plan to build 16 tiny houses in Nelstad
near the timber gardens between the
Beukenhof and the Horst has been canceled.  The
project developer will not proceed with
his idea after the municipal council and
local residents
expressed negative views about the plans on Tuesday evening.  No,
I'm not going to get that here.  No, no,
No.
Several council members indicated that they found the
idea for the tiny houses sympathetic in itself
, but they
blame the project developer for having
done far too little to involve the neighborhood in
the plans. And the neighborhood is
now making it known en masse that they are opposed.
Land is as close to an inastic resource as.
The ability to use it while completely
should be seen as monopolistic behavior.
But there is another
incentive involved, and that is that the
moment you know you
can cause someone else a lot of damage, that
other person might well start making a trade-off
. Yes, but I don't feel like
going through the procedure here, because for you, if you
win, you have indeed stopped the plan
. That costs, uh, sometimes in
some cases really millions to
be stopped. And if you lose,
you are out €8,000. And then a lot of
objectors say to such a
project developer: "Well, if you do
n't want to go through that procedure with me, say after 2.5 years, then just buy me
off."
And then you make money, and then you make
money from the fact that  we now
have a housing shortage and that there are children
homeless on
reasonable damages and put on opers
new
truly interesting people stop the
conversation around the mortgage
mortgage deductions the v day will
pretend like it's a big deal to be
against it other parties will act like
it's a silver
SC
tax on property owners who
not people
in a country that is aging rapidly
that's the right difficult decision
still though, the lasting problem with
taxes on property is that it can
unfairly penalize those who improve
their homes and build new and better
places
fewadics
dut ministry of financeortun
for introduction land tax prom hous
indry in they adm a general tax on the
value of all land can be fitted into the
existing property tax and is a very
efficient way to obtain tax money no
unwanted behavioral effects occur it can
yield aicant revenue with which
municipal
interesti true
tax on land lead precisely to effent use
of scare space a sufficiently high
general land tax would cause immediate and
instantial drop in land vales this tax
would not be distortionar it would not
be regressive and  it would
distribute even that was artificially
inflated
chyconic
growth equality use of scar land without
environmentalruption
as well how to build new houses years
cre bades i would maybe just maybe
talking about high land tax in a tiny
country with the highest population in
Europe
won do that new might
than you foring this video is more
opinion than usual I'm sorry if that's
really frustrating years of me living
here that some anno
I definitely w to hear critiques against
the general countries also especially on the
de eigen Woning for fed as opposed to
the mortgage aftrack you can watch the
full Dutch interview with Robiette on my
new channel ruis unfortunately You will
be DCH English subtitles